Finding Aid for Fountain Street Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.) Records 1856-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fountain Street Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.) records 1856-1978
Fountain Street Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.)
16 linear feet
Minutes and other records of the church's governing board; pastors' files, including sermons, addresses and publications; and administrative records of the church office, including reports, publications, treasurer's files, correspondence, and subject files; also photographs.
86975 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The church deposited its early records with the library in 1978. Donor no. 6229.
The record group is open for research.
Fountain Street Church traces its history to the founding in 1826 of a Baptist missionary church in what would later become Grand Rapids. In 1837 the "Thomas Mission" became the First Baptist Church of Grand Rapids. By 1848 the congregation of First Baptist worshipped at a church located at Crescent and Division streets. Twenty years later the congregation moved to a small building located on the corner of Fountain and Bostwick streets.
By 1856 another group of Baptists had arrived in Grand Rapids and organized their own congregation, Second Baptist Church. The two congregations voted to merge in 1869, forming the Baptist Church of Grand Rapids under the leadership of pastor Samuel Graves.
One of the primary objectives of the newly united congregation was to erect a new church structure. In May, 1872, they began construction on a new building located at the site of the First Baptist Church's building. The lecture room was occupied in December, 1873. Construction was halted for several years thereafter because of the bankruptcy of the contractor and the failure of many to make good on their pledges due to the Panic of 1873. Construction was resumed in 1876 and the edifice was completed the next year.
The attempt to create a single Baptist congregation within the city was never wholly successful. In 1883 fifty-five members of the Baptist Church of Grand Rapids (which apparently now became known commonly as Fountain St. Baptist Church) were dismissed and formed a new Second Baptist Church. In 1885 about as many persons were dismissed to form Wealthy Avenue Baptist Church. In 1888 another group formed Calvary Church and in 1892 a fourth group left Fountain Street Church to found Berean Church.
Apparently there was little or no rancor between the mother church and the various offspring. The pastor of Fountain Street Church preached the dedication sermon at Second Baptist, Wealthy Ave., and Calvary churches. Members of Fountain Street Church contributed financially towards the construction of buildings for the Wealthy St., Calvary and Berean congregations.
In 1885 K.B. Tupper replaced Rev. Graves as pastor of Fountain Street Church. In turn he was replaced by John L. Jackson in 1890, who remained with the congregation until 1896. While Jackson offended some members by flirting with liberal ideas, his successor J. Herman Randall created intense controversy by openly rejecting belief in the literal truth of the Bible, embracing the evolutionary thesis, and preferring ethical to biblical themes in his sermons.
When Randall left Fountain Street in 1906 a bitter controversy developed within the congregation over whether his replacement should be another modernist or a more traditional Baptist. Eventually the church called A.W. Wishart, a noted proponent of the social gospel. Wishart, who remained pastor until 1933, alienated fundamentalists by his views.
In 1917 fire completely destroyed the building that had been erected in the 1870's. Services were held in the Power's Theater (later called the Midtown) until a new structure could be built. In June of 1922 construction was begun on the site of the old building, the cornerstone being laid in November of that year. The new church structure was dedicated February 3, 1924.
In 1933 Rev. Milton S. McGorrill was chosen to lead the congregation. He was succeeded in 1944 by Duncan Littlefair. During Rev. Littlefair's pastorate the church has renounced its affiliation with the American Baptist Convention and become non-denominational.
The records of Fountain Street Church are divided into three groups: (1) the files of the governing board, (2) the records of various pastors, and (3) the church's office files. Taken together these documents give an excellent view of the congregation's history since 1869. There is also a small series of photographs.
Subjects:
Baptists--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Fountain Street Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Liberalism (Religion)--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Littlefair, Duncan Elliot, 1912-; McGorrill, Milton S.; Randall, J. Herman.; Wishart, Alfred Wesley, 1865-1933.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Baptist churches--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Churches--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Fountain Street Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Churches.; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sermons.
- Governing Board Files 1856-1945
  The governing board's records are complete from 1867 to 1942. The Church retains the files created after 1942. All of the records were kept in large, bound volumes. Originally the minutes of most meetings held under the auspices of the church, whether of the governing board or not, were recorded in these volumes but eventually non-governing board material was excluded.
  - Trustee and Advisory Boards
    - 1856-1861 (Box 1)
    - 1867-1899 (Box 1)
    - 1899-1910 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1922 (Box 1)
    - 1923-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929-1935 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 2)
    - 1939-1942 (Box 2)
  - Church notes and minutes
    - 1869-1886 (Box 2)
    - 1887-1901 (Box 2)
    - 1901-1917 (Box 2)
  - Board of Deacons
    - 1910-1920 (Box 2)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 2)
- Pastors' files
  Records of the Reverends J. Herman Randall, Alfred W. Wishart, Milton S. McGorrill and Duncan Littlefair are found in the pastor's file. Except for the Duncan Littlefair subseries, most of the material here consists of printed sermons, public lectures, or publications. The sermons of Duncan Littlefair covering the years 1944-1963 have been indexed. Also included for Littlefair are his files of correspondence and materials relating to his ministerial work.
  - J. Herman Randall
    - Sermons, 1904-1906, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Alfred Wesley Wishart
    - University of Chicago student notes circa 1893, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Trenton, N.J. material circa 1900-1906 (Box 3)
    - Primary Facts in Religious Thoughts by A.W. Wishart 1905 (Box 3)
    - Sermons and Publications 1908-1915
      - 1908-1915 (Box 3)
      - 1916-1920 (Box 3)
      - 1921, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1924-1927 Sermons and Publications (Box 3)
      - 1928 (Box 3)
        (including debate of AWW and Clarence Darrow on "General Purpose in the Universe")
      - 1929-1931 (Box 3)
    - Lessons on the Bible 1931-1933, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Funeral Service of A.W.W. 1933 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts, 11 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous notebook material, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Milton S. McGorrill
    - Sermons (Box 3)
    - Personal correspondence
      - 1937 (Box 3)
      - 1938-1939, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Duncan Littlefair
    - Sermons, addresses and publications
      - 1944-1959, 16 folders (Box 4)
      - 1960-1972, 13 folders (Box 5)
      - 1973-1978, 5 folders (Box 6)
        (lacking 1977)
    - The Glory Within You circa 1973 (Box 6)
    - Sin Comes of Age circa 1975 (Box 6)
    - Index to Sermons (1944-1963) and press releases re. books (Box 6)
    - Dictaphone recordings of sermons (Box 6)
    - Biographical information (Box 14)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 14)
    - Speeches (Box 14)
    - Writings (Box 14)
    - Ministerial work (funerals, weddings, etc.) (Box 14)
    - Church administration (staff fund raising) (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1940s-1950s (Box 14)
      - A-G (Box 14)
      - H-Z (Box 15)
    - General Correspondence
      - 1954-1962 (Box 15)
      - 1962-1969 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1960s-1972 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence re "Today Show" appearance 1973 (Box 16)
    - Phonograph record of Littlefair sermon (s) (Box 16)
      (stored with library's phonograph disk collection)
- Office files 1869-1978
  The office files of the church represent items of a routine nature primarily retained by the church secretary. Unfortunately filing methods, the policy regarding retirement of records, and subject headings varied from secretary to secretary. To help eliminate confusion a year by year arrangement, as well as standardized subject headings, were imposed upon the office files. After 1935, however, the church records were maintained on a "year" which did not correspond to the calendar year. Thus folders listed for a given year may contain materials from either the preceding or succeeding year.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Historical materials, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 7)
    - Round Table material (Box 7)
    - Bible Study material, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - 1869-1934
    - Membership records 1869-1896 (Box 7)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity 1883-1934 (Box 7)
    - Baptist City Mission Society 1893-1910
      - 1893-1910 (Box 7)
      - 1914-1928 (Box 7)
    - Building committee 1917-1924 (Box 7)
    - Lectures and concerts 1924-1932 (Box 7)
    - Treasurer's files 1932-1934 (Box 7)
  - 1935
    - Annual reports (Box 7)
    - Treasurer's files (Box 7)
  - 1936
    - Annual reports (Box 7)
    - Public schools, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 7)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 7)
  - 1937
    - Board of Deacons (Box 8)
    - Directory (Box 8)
    - Education (Box 8)
    - Engagements (Box 8)
    - Kalamazoo College (Box 8)
    - Kelford, Rev. E.A (Box 8)
    - Michigan Baptist Convention (including pre 1937) (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Organist (Box 8)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 8)
    - Rotary, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Sunday Evening Lectures (Box 8)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 8)
  - 1938
    - American Legion (Box 8)
    - Anti-Tuberculosis Society (Box 8)
    - Bible School (Box 8)
    - Board of Deacons (Box 8)
    - Brochure and Appreciation letters (Box 8)
    - Drama (Box 8)
    - Engagements (Box 8)
    - Friendship night (Box 8)
    - Kalamazoo College (Box 8)
    - McGorrill Lectures (Box 8)
    - Men's Club (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Movements (Box 8)
    - Organist (Box 8)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 8)
    - Rotary, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Special file (Box 8)
    - Sunday Evening Lectures, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - T Club (Box 8)
    - Travel Fund (Box 8)
    - Treasurer's File (Box 8)
    - United Simmer Sermons (Box 8)
    - Ushers (Box 8)
  - 1939
    - Anti-Tuberculosis League (Box 8)
    - Appreciation Letters (Box 8)
    - Bible School (Box 8)
    - Board of Trustees (Box 8)
    - Church Study Group (examining church goals) (Box 8)
    - Drama (Box 8)
    - Engagements (Box 8)
    - Kalamazoo College (Box 8)
    - Men's Club (Box 8)
    - Michigan Baptist Convention (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Movements (Box 9)
    - Northern Baptist Convention (Box 9)
    - Politics (Box 9)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 9)
    - Rotary (Box 9)
    - Special file (Box 9)
    - Sunday Evenings, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file-Bonds (Box 9)
  - 1940
    - Annual reports (Box 9)
    - Appreciation letters (Box 9)
    - Bible school (Box 9)
    - Boy scouts (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
  - 1941
    - Governing Board (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
  - 1942
    - Governing Board (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
  - 1943
    - Annual reports (Box 9)
    - Mailings to congregation (Box 9)
    - Servicemen's letters (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
  - 1944
    - Annual reports (Box 9)
    - Church organization (Box 9)
    - Lists (Box 9)
    - Mailings to congregation (Box 9)
    - Men's Lunch (Box 9)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 9)
    - Servicemen's letters (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
  - 1945
    - Annual reports (Box 9)
    - Committees (Box 9)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Kent County) (Box 9)
    - Kent County Youth Guidance Commission (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - North Baptist Convention (Box 9)
    - Penny Social (Box 9)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 9)
    - Sermons, comments on (Box 9)
    - Servicemen's letters (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
  - 1946
    - Annual reports (Box 9)
    - Council of Social agencies (Kent County) (Box 9)
    - Council of Social agencies (Kent County)- racial (Box 9)
    - Governing Board (Box 9)
    - Kent County Youth Guidance Commission (Box 9)
    - Mailings to congregation (Box 9)
    - Men's Lunch (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 9)
    - Sermons, comments on (Box 9)
    - Servicemen's letters (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file-monthly reports (Box 9)
    - Veteran's Council (Box 9)
  - 1947
    - Annual reports (Box 9)
    - Civil forum (Box 9)
    - Correspondence from other churches (Box 9)
    - Council of Churches (Kent County) (Box 9)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Kent County) (Box 9)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Kent County)- racial (Box 9)
    - Governing Board (Box 9)
    - Kent County Youth Guidance Commission (Box 9)
    - Men's Lunch (Box 9)
    - Publications, programs and publicity (Box 9)
    - Sermons, comments on (Box 9)
    - Treasurer's file
      - General (Box 10)
      - Chapel drive (Box 10)
      - Financial canvass (Box 10)
      - Monthly reports (Box 10)
    - Veteran's Council (Box 10)
    - Worship (Box 10)
  - 1948
    - Annual reports (Box 10)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Box 10)
    - Council of Social Agencies-Displaced persons (Box 10)
    - Council of Social Agencies-racial (Box 10)
    - Church Night Dinners (Box 10)
    - Governing Board (Box 10)
    - Lists (Box 10)
    - Minutes (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Lists (Box 10)
    - Mailings to congregations (Box 10)
    - Membership (Box 10)
    - Men's Lunch (Box 10)
    - Mental Health (Box 10)
    - Organist (Box 10)
    - Radio Broadcasts (Box 10)
    - Religion and Business (Box 10)
    - Sermons, comments on (Box 10)
    - Treasurer's file (Box 10)
    - Report to Governing Board (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Monthly reports (Box 10)
    - United World Federalists (Box 10)
    - Worship (Box 10)
  - 1949
    - Annual reports (Box 10)
    - Bookstore (Box 10)
    - Chapel rehabilitation (Box 10)
    - Community Activities (Box 10)
    - Church Night Dinners (Box 10)
    - Community Guild (Box 10)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Kent County) (Box 10)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Kent County)-Displaced Persons (Box 10)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Kent County)-Racial (Box 10)
    - Extension Service (Box 10)
    - Governing Board-
      - Correspondence (Box 10)
      - Materials sent to (Box 10)
      - Organizational chart (Box 10)
    - Inter-Club Council (Box 10)
    - Mailings to Congregation (Box 10)
    - Membership (Box 10)
    - Men's Club (Box 10)
    - Men's Lunch (Box 10)
    - Ministerial Students (Box 10)
    - Missions (Box 10)
    - Northern Baptist Convention (Box 10)
    - Round Table (Box 10)
    - Sermons; comments on (Box 10)
    - Strength Thru the Spirit Committee (Box 10)
    - Treasurer's Files
      - Budget (Box 11)
      - Monthly reports (Box 11)
      - Reports (Box 11)
      - Special Fund Drive (Box 11)
    - Williams Fellowship (Box 11)
    - Willow Run Community Council (Box 11)
    - Women's Groups (Box 11)
  - 1950
    - Annual reports (Box 11)
    - Character Research Project (Box 11)
    - Church Council (Box 11)
    - Church Night Dinners (Box 11)
    - Community Activities (Box 11)
    - Community Guild (Box 11)
    - Council of Churches-Kent County (Box 11)
    - Council of Churches-Michigan (Box 11)
    - Council of Social Agencies (Box 11)
    - Council of Social Agencies-Displaced Persons (Box 11)
    - Council of Social Agencies-Racial (Box 11)
    - Extension Service of the University of Michigan (Box 11)
    - Governing Board (Box 11)
    - Mailings to Congregation (Box 11)
    - Membership (Box 11)
    - Men's Lunch (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - School of Personal Psychology (Box 11)
    - Albert Schweitzer Day (Box 11)
    - Sermons, comments on (Box 11)
    - Special Planning Commission Report (Box 11)
    - Treasurer's File
      - Chapel drive (Box 11)
      - Financial canvass (Box 11)
      - Fund drive (Box 11)
      - Monthly reports (Box 11)
    - Worship (Box 11)
  - 1951
    - Annual reports (Box 11)
    - Character Research Project (Box 11)
    - Church Council (Box 11)
    - Community Activities (Box 11)
    - Community Guild (Box 11)
    - Council of Social Agencies displaced persons (Box 11)
    - Governing Board (Box 11)
    - Mailings to congregation (Box 11)
    - Membership (Box 11)
    - Music (Box 11)
    - Sermons, comments on (Box 11)
    - Treasurer's File-Chapel drive (Box 11)
    - Vocational Guidance Commission (Box 11)
    - Worship (Box 11)
  - 1952
    - Annual reports (Box 11)
    - Business Affairs Committee (Box 11)
    - Church Council (Box 11)
    - Community Guild (Box 11)
    - Education (Box 11)
    - Externship (Box 11)
    - Governing Board (Box 11)
    - Mailings to Congregation (Box 11)
    - Membership (Box 11)
    - Overview Lectures (Box 11)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
    - Albert Schweitzer Day (Box 12)
    - Treasurer's File (Box 12)
    - Worship (Box 12)
  - 1953
    - Annual reports (Box 12)
    - Business Affairs Committee, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Character Education Workshop (Box 12)
    - Church Council (Box 12)
    - Church Directory (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Correspondence with Owen Lattimore (includes earlier correspondence to 1949) (Box 12)
    - Externship (Box 12)
    - Overview Lectures (Box 12)
    - Peace Conference (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
    - Treasurer's File (Box 12)
    - Treasurer's File-monthly reports (Box 12)
    - Women's Organization (Box 12)
    - Worship (Box 12)
  - 1954
    - Annual Reports (Box 12)
    - Character Research Project (Box 12)
    - Church Council (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Governing Board (Box 12)
    - Mailings to Congregation (Box 12)
    - Membership (Box 12)
    - Publications, Program and Publicity (Box 12)
    - Treasurer's File (Box 12)
    - Worship (Box 12)
  - 1955
    - Beliefs (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Mailings to Congregation (Box 12)
    - Overview Lectures (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
  - 1956
    - Annual Reports (Box 12)
    - Beliefs (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Externship (Box 12)
    - Mailings to Congregation (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
  - 1957
    - Annual Reports (Box 12)
    - Character School (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Mailings to Congregation (Box 12)
    - Publications, Program and Publicity (Box 12)
  - 1958
    - Annual Reports (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
  - 1959
    - Annual reports (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
    - Religious Education (Box 12)
    - Service Committee (Box 12)
  - 1960
    - Annual Reports (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
  - 1961
    - Annual Reports (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
    - Randall Fulfillment Project (Box 12)
  - 1962
    - Annual reports (Box 12)
    - Community Guild (Box 12)
    - Correspondence (Box 12)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 12)
    - Randall Fulfillment Project (Box 12)
  - 1963
    - Annual reports (Box 13)
    - Community Guild (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Randall Fulfillment Project (Box 13)
  - 1964
    - Annual Reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
  - 1965
    - Annual Reports (Box 13)
    - Community Guild (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
  - 1966
    - Annual reports (Box 13)
    - Community Guild (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1967
    - Annual Reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1968
    - Annual reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Randall Fulfillment Project (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1969
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
  - 1970
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1971
    - Annual Reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1972
    - Annual Reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1973
    - Annual reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1974
    - Fiftieth Anniversary of church building (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1975
    - Annual reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1976
    - Annual reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1977
    - Annual Reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
  - 1978
    - Annual Reports (Box 13)
    - Publications, Programs and Publicity (Box 13)
    - Women's Association (Box 13)
- Photographs, 2 folders (Box 13)
  The Photos includes pictures of the 1977 church fire; church construction, 1950; and photos of Albert Schweitzer visiting church in 1949.7